ANOOP MACHARLA

Certified Cloud Engineer

AI Engineer 🔸

Entrepreneur

Open Source Contributor

noop2016@gmail.com | 615-266-6715 | learnwithapprentice.com | https://linkedin.com/in/amacharla | Austin, TX

SUMMARY

Spearheaded automation initiatives with over 7 years of experience, co-founding Apprentice, Sparkist Technologies, and Conlangio. Led global teams to architect autoscaled microservices on AWS and GCP, ensuring scalability and security, while implementing AI tools that boosted team performance by 2 weeks (saved) and increased customer retention by 20%. Experienced in AI, serverless computing, cloud infrastructure, and technical leadership.

SKILLS

- Languages: Python, C, Bash, MySQL, Flutter, JavaScript
- Engineering Tools: Flutter Flow, Kubernetes, AWS, GCP, Git, Jenkins X, Firebase, Supabase
- AI Stack: Generative AI, n8n, MCP Servers, RAG, LangChain, Docker, Agents
- Databases: Postgres, Rocksandra (Cassandra + RocksDB), Vitess, MariaDB, MySQL
- Soft Skills: Presentation, Leadership, Problem-Solving, Customer Obsessed, Mentorship

WORK EXPERIENCE

Technical CoFounder, Apprentice Austin, USA

Jan 2024 - Present

As the Founder and CEO of Apprentice, I bootstrapped and scaled a <u>two-sided edtech marketplace</u>, cultivating a high-performing team that collaboratively achieved significant milestones. My leadership responsibilities included:

- Architected and prototyped scalable applications integrating AI tools, accelerating platform iterations, and demonstrating LLM integration potential.
- Led data-driven product strategy, leveraging in-depth customer engagement and analysis to align development with startup needs, significantly enhancing user adoption and satisfaction.
- Spearheaded global operational expansion and cultivated high-performing technical teams, actively fostering startup ecosystem collaboration and enabling rapid development cycles.
- Designed and managed robust custom microservices across AWS and GCP, ensuring scalable and reliable architectures critical for all applications.
- Developed compelling technical demos and proof-of-concept solutions, effectively showcasing the startup's growth potential and tangible business utility to key stakeholders.
- Drove cross-functional alignment between business objectives and technical implementation, consistently leading to successful product deployments.

Lab DevOps & Events Engineer, AWS Training & Certification Org New York, USA

Jun 2020 - Jan 2024

- INCW IOIN, ODA
- Championed automation (Python, Jenkins, and AI) to reduce team workload by 30%.
- Drove operational excellence through SOPs and code refactoring, accelerating service scaling by 50%.
- Re-architected customer experience by upgrading systems and processes used at AWS Summits/Re:Invent, cutting onsite issues by 70%.
- Built a key internal metrics application, providing leadership with monthly insights on product and resources.
- Led security efforts, preventing 80% of lab resources from fraud/abuse via reverse engineering and collaboration with service teams.
- $\bullet \quad \text{Fostered innovation by implementing generative AI for Lab developers, achieving 60\% AI-generated labs}.$

DevOps Engineer, LiquidX Inc

Feb 2020 - Jun 2020

Boston, USA

- Engineered a secure build and release pipeline via Azure DevOps, reducing deployment errors by 30%.
- Implemented HashiCorp Vault for applications access control and secret handling, enhancing security compliance for SOC2.
- Designed and terraformed the entire AWS infrastructure in a modular manner, improving scalability and reducing provisioning time.
- Optimized AWS resources by cleaning up unused assets, saving over \$3,000/month on AWS costs.
- Configured monitoring and alerting of Kubernetes & AWS resources via Datadog and Opsgenie, decreasing incident response time.

- Boston, USA
- Engineered and deployed stateful, redundant database systems including Postgres with custom extensions and Rocksandra on Kubernetes, enhancing system robustness and scalability.
- Automated containerization and pipeline processes using Docker, RPMs, and monitoring tools, improving deployment efficiency and system observability.
- Developed and executed stress testing strategies (TPC-H, TPC-DS) for Postgres databases, ensuring performance stability under high transactional loads.
- Delivered live technical presentations at AWS reInvent 2018 demonstrating Vitess cluster deployment achieving 1 million queries per second, showcasing expertise in large-scale database performance optimization.

EDUCATION

M.B.A. in Entrepreneurship, Oneday

Jan 2024 - Present

London, UK

Certificate in Full Stack Engineering, Holberton School San Francisco, USA

• 2-year coding school.

B.S. in Business Management – Finance, Stony Brook University Stony Brook, USA

Jan 2012 - Dec 2016